Hello all. Can you hear me?
>> Yes.
Okay, good.
Let's wait a few seconds. Again, as
always, uh when in doubt, please either
speak up or post a question on chat.
I'll only be looking at the chat
periodically. So, uh if you post a
question on chat, either one of my TAs
will reply to you or I will reply but
with some delay. Okay, let's begin.
So uh
can anybody remind me what we discussed
in the last class?
Anyone?
>> What did we discuss?
>> Neurons.
>> History of neural networks, neural
networks, perceptrons, NLP. Thank you.
Right. So we saw a bit of what neural
networks are. We're going to continue
with the theme and in this class we're
going to see what a network can
represent. We'll continue a bit from
where we left off. We will discuss what
neural networks can represent and the
restrictions on their capacity and how
these relate to their activation
functions and depth and width.
So quick recap as we saw in the last
class in a great many AI tasks tasks
that were previously considered to be
solely in the domain of human expertise
these have now been successfully taken
over by artificial neural networks.
These include tasks like voice
recognition, machine translation, image
captioning, intelligence games and
pretty much everything that you can
think of these days. So what are all
these amazing neural networks that do
all these great things? In each case,
the neural network is a function that
takes in some input and produces some
output. So an input voice signal
produces a transcription. An input image
produces a caption. An input game state
produces a prediction for the next best
move and so on. But what's in these
functions?
If a human were to perform these tasks,
these functions were computed by the
human brain. And so neural networks
mimic the network structure in the
brain.
And we also saw that the brain in turn
is a giant network of neurons where the
neurons themselves are these little
units that fire when the combined input
exceeds a threshold. And so artificial
neural networks are also networks of
computational models of the neuron which
again look like this. And these models
of the neuron are what we will call
perceptrons. And so again a perceptron
is this unit that receives many inputs.
It has a weight associated with each
input.
The weight is a real number. So since
each input has a corresponding weight,
you can compute a weighted sum of all of
the inputs.
And if the weighted sum exceeds a
threshold, then the neuron in the in the
simplest case, the neuron, the
perceptron outputs a one. And if the
weighted sum does not exceed the
threshold, it outputs a zero. In
electrical electrical engineering terms,
this perceptron is a threshold gate and
implements threshold logic. So remember
this term, we're going to see it again.
Now let's sort of redo this math a
little bit
here. Right here, uh, we say that the
perceptron computes summation wi.
Actually, this color is horrible. Let me
get a better color. So it computes
summation
wi
xi, where the x's are the inputs and the
w's are the weights. And if this is
greater than a threshold t it outputs a
one otherwise it outputs a zero. I can
rewrite this in this manner right. I can
say [clears throat]
it computes summation wi
x i
minus t
z equals and if z is greater than zero
it outputs a one it outputs a zero
otherwise. So, does everybody agree that
this thing to the right is the same as
the rule to the left? Is everybody with
me on this?
Fairly straightforward, right? But then
once I write it like so, I can do it
slightly differently. I can say Z equals
summation wi XI
minus T. And then I can define this
operator theta which operates on Z where
theta Z equals 1
if
Z is greater than equal to 0 and zero
otherwise.
And so again this
comb the combination of these two
operations fully defines the perceptron.
Yes or no? Do you agree by this?
This exactly the same operation as
before.
So do you agree with this?
Yes. No. Okay guys do me a favor.
there's a little thumbs up uh or I think
it's a thumbs up that you can give on
Zoom. So when I ask you a question, you
just give me a thumbs up. I'll wait for
everybody to give me a thumbs up and
then I'll proceed. So but this is easy.
This is kind of easy, right? And so if I
can write things in this manner that
means I can partition the uh
uh network the unit into these two two
operations. First I comput Z
which is an aphine function of the input
and then you apply the simple rule
on the Z. Now what's the difference
between linear and aphine? Again do you
guys remember the difference between
linear and fine?
What's the difference between linear and
fine?
The intercept right? So if I have
something like summation wixi,
this is a linear. But if I have
summation wxi
plus b,
that's an fi function. And how do you
know whether it's linear or alpha? If
you equate it to zero, this plot will go
through origin. If you equate this term
to zero, it does it's still going to be
planer, but it will not go through
origin. It can intercept anywhere.
That's the difference between linear and
aphine. And so this perceptron is now
can be restated as first computing an
aine term which is summation wi xr + v
and then putting that aine term z
through this operator where the output
is one. If the alphine term is greater
than zero and zero otherwise and once I
draw it in this manner I can take one
more step and I can separate the whole
thing into two steps.
I can first say I compute a Z
and then I compute theta of Z. And what
does theta look like? Theta of Z is this
function which output which takes the
value one whenever the output is input Z
is positive and takes the value zero
otherwise and so the perceptron can be
rewritten as first computing the aine
term Z and then putting the Z through a
theta of Z this function which outputs a
one whenever the Z whenever Z is
positive and zero otherwise. So this is
also exactly the same perceptron as we
saw before.
Is this making sense to everybody?
Yes. No,
guys. Okay.
So I don't see any thumbs up, but I'm
assuming I'm getting a Can you guys hear
me?
>> There are millions of thumbs up, sir.
>> Okay, perfect.
>> So all right, this is great. But then
once I separate things out in this
manner, right? I don't need to retain a
uh just the threshold, I can make theta
of Z somewhat different. In the first
case, we had theta of Z was something
that looked like this
zero here and then went up and then one.
But instead of having something that
jumps so suddenly, I can have something
that goes smoother like so. And that is
a sigmoid. Now you can see how the
sigmoid works. So if z is a very large
negative number like minus infinity then
x of e ra to minus of minus infinity
is e ra to infinity
which is infinity itself and so this
function becomes 1 / 1 + infinity
which is zero. Right? So when z is a
very large negative number this function
is zero. When z is a very large positive
so out here it's going to be zero. When
z is a very large positive number then
you have again e ra to z which is say e
ra to infinity
e ra to minus z right is e ra to minus
infinity. Let me do this cleanly.
One sec.
And so I can say x of minus infinity
this is going to be simply zero right.
And so this term becomes 1 / 1 + 0
which is 1. And so when z is a large
positive number this is one. When z is a
large negative number this is zero. And
because this is a smooth function in
between is going to vary smoothly like
so. And so this sigmoid function is
basically a smoother function of the
threshold activation. And having the
smoother function has all kinds of uh uh
benefits that we will see later. Right?
So we can now write the
uh perceptron like so. We first compute
an aphine value and then put it through
a function which could be a a threshold
function or a smoother version of a
sigmoid. But we can also have other
activations like this tanh which is
basically the same as the sigmoine but
centered at zero. So it goes from minus1
to one. Or you can have this
rectification function where the output
of this activ of this function is the
same as the input when the input is
positive but zero if the input is
negative or you can have the smooth
version of it which is the soft plus. So
in every case this function
there's a the operation is a two-step
process. First you compute this aphine
value Z and then you put the aphine
value through a function which could be
a threshold a sigmoid a tan h or
whatever. This function is called an
activation function
and different activation functions will
give you different behaviors for the
perceptron. But for the moment, we're
going to continue to assume a threshold
activation because a threshold
activation is actually really nice to
develop intuitions about what's what the
how the perceptron behaves. So that
leads us to our first poll.
Let me ask this.
Can you guys see the poll?
15 seconds, guys.
All right, let me stop this.
Okay, can anybody tell me uh if this
first one is linear or fine? What is it?
The first one. Second second one
>> linear aine.
>> Fine. Right. because you have a plus4.
Third one, this is an aine function
>> linear.
>> Yeah,
>> functions are also a function. So this
is an aphine function. A linear case is
a special case aine function. And the
fourth one
aine, right? So the first and the third
are linear but they are also aphine. The
first, third and fourth are all happen.
Now let's continue with this. So
now a multi-layer perceptron or an MLP
is a network of such perceptrons where
the perceptrons receive input from other
perceptrons and they feed by other
perceptrons in the in the subsequent
layer. We'll see a formal definition of
what a layer is in a few minutes.
So when these networks have many such
layers is supposed to be deep networks.
What is the formal notion of depth in
this context? Does anybody have any idea
what's the formal notion of depth in
this context?
>> The number of layers
>> the number of layers. But there's
something more to it. Uh to answer
someone why this is aphine. This is an
aphine where the intercept is zero.
That's all. Okay, so let's go there.
There's a formal definition of deep
structures in any directed graph with
sources. Sources are nodes from which
you only have outgoing edges and syncs
where nodes where you have only incoming
edges. The depth of the graph is simply
the length of the path which is the
number of edges on the longest path from
the source to the sync. So here in this
left plot, although there's a path of
length one, there's a path of length
two. So the depth of this graph is two.
Here this is the source. This is the
sync. You have paths of length one,
length two and length three. But the
longest path is length length three. So
the depth of this graph is three.
So we uh say a graph is deep if the
depth is at least three. The same
principle can be applied to networks.
And in the computation of a neural
network, the computation is generally
directed. All the data goes from the
input and flows unidirectionally towards
the output.
So the depth of the network is the
longest length of the longest path that
is the maximum number of perceptrons or
neurons from input to output. So in this
first figure you can see that the depth
of the network is three.
Since the longest path is three in this
figure, what is the depth of this
network to the top?
Anybody? What is the depth of this
network
over here?
It's two, right? One, two. What about
this guy over here?
The one to the bottom right. What's the
depth of that one?
That's four. Although there are paths of
length two and three, the actual depth
of the network is four. So, you get the
idea, right?
And if the depth of the network is at
least three meaning it has at least
the you know to go from the input to the
output. The longest path is at least
length three then the network is subset
to be deep. So a deep network is the one
where the depth of the output neurons is
at least three. It has to be greater
than two. Is this definition making
sense to everybody?
at least three three layers.
So
what I see one yes
okay I bet what's your doubt here
so here the input goes to one layer the
second layer and the third layer so this
is a deep network on the other hand if
you had only two layers if the network
were only until here then the input
would go into one layer and then the
next layer this is not deep so you need
to have at least three layers for the
network to be called D. So uh that's the
formal definition.
But then how do you define a layer?
Does anybody know how you define a layer
in this context? I mean I'm just freely
talking about layers. What's a layer?
Anyone?
Input output.
So
here's how you define a layer. A layer
is the uh set of all neurons that have
the same depth from the input. This
network has four layers. Can you
identify which neurons are in the first
layer? Anybody?
Can you identify the neurons in the
first layer?
So
there are four neurons in the first
layer.
These four red they all have it doesn't
matter how I draw the network right
these four red neurons all have depth
one with respect to the input so these
four neurons are layer one these three
green neurons all have depth two with
respect to the input meaning the longest
path to these neurons is too long and so
these three neurons form the second
layer only these two yellow neurons form
the third layer because the longest path
to these yellow neurons from any input
as length three and the two blue neurons
are the fourth layer. So as the idea of
a layer coming across a layer is the set
of all neurons that have the same depth
with respect to the input that come
across everybody. Everybody
yes no I'm assuming you there's a lot of
yeses okay so let's move on
so here's how we defined our multi-layer
perceptron it's a network of perceptrons
which
uh I will generally also call neurons
sometimes after we're talking of neural
networks the nodes in the networks and
neurons are perceptrons the edges
represent uh the connections between the
perceptrons that each edge carries a
weight. The network performs
computations. It takes an input and
produces an output. The inputs can be
real or boolean. The outputs too can be
boolean or real value. And we've mostly
shown networks with a single output so
far, but in fact the network can have
multiple outputs or a vector of outputs.
So overall the network in fact
represents a function that embodies an
input output relationship between inputs
and outputs. The question is what kind
of input output relationships can this
network model? What kind of functions
can it compute?
Now we've already seen that MLPS can
compose boolean functions. It can
operate on boolean inputs and produce
boolean outputs like this network to the
left. We also saw that networks can
compose classifiers, functions that work
on real valued input and output whether
the input belongs to a class or not. And
we saw that MLPS can also compose re
real valued functions. Take in a real
valued input and produce a real valued
output. For instance, we saw in the last
class how to construct a network that
approximately computes this blue curve,
the function shown by this blue curve.
But what are the limitations? Can we
always construct a network to compute
any function or are there limitations on
what kinds of functions we can compute
with a network? And if so, what are
they? So
that is the topic of for the rest of
today's lecture.
Give me a you know we will see that
multi-layer perceptrons are universal
boolean functions. Give me any boolean
function I can compute an M construct an
MLP to compute it. In this context we'll
discuss why it's necessary for the
networks to be deep. We'll also see that
they are universal classifiers. Give me
an arbitrary decision boundary. I can
construct an MLP that captures it
arbitrarily precisely.
Again we'll discuss the need for network
to be teeth and finally we'll see that
MLPs are universal approximators. Give
me any input output relationship at all
and I can construct an MLP that
approximates it to arbitrary precision
and in this context context we'll
discuss the issue of optimal width and
depth of the network.
So first we'll discuss the topic of
MLPS's universal boolean functions. Now
we all know that MLPS can model boolean
functions. But how well how well do they
do it? Now we know that individual
perceptrons can model boolean functions.
We saw these figures in the last class.
They show how a perceptron can model the
and not or or and or gates. To remind
you in this figure the numbers on top of
the edges represent the weights. The
numbers in the circles represent the
thresholds. The perceptron outputs a one
if the total weighted input matches or
exceeds the threshold. So in this figure
to the left if x is one and y is one the
total input is two and then this
perceptron the total input matches two
and this perceptron fires. If either x
or y were zero then the total input
would be less than two and so this would
not fire. So this is n. What kind of
gate was that one?
Uh that's an and what was this over
here? We saw this in the last class.
That was an R. And this guy we saw was a
not right. We understood this.
But then a perceptron can do a lot more
than than just this computation. So the
perceptron is in fact a universal and
gate. This perceptron will only fire if
all of these guys are one and all of
these guys are zero. So let's see how if
these guys are zero that see the weights
the total input is L because you have L
once and the rest are zeros and so this
will fire but if any one of them becomes
these become zero then the total input
will become less than one less than L
because that corresponding line no
longer contributes to the aine term and
so it will not fire. Similarly, if any
of these guys becomes a one because the
weight is minus one, this will actually
subtract from the sum and the total sum
will become less than 10. And then once
again, this unit will not fire. So this
unit only fires if all of these guys are
one and these guys are zero. So this is
a universal and gate. So is this uh did
this make sense to you guys
over here? Does this make sense to?
Okay. Similarly, this one here is what I
call a universal orgate. This will fire
if any of these guys are one or if any
of these guys are zero. And to let's see
how that works. Let's start with the
only condition under which it doesn't
fire. So when all of these are zero and
all of these guys are one. When all of
these guys are zero and all of these
guys are one then the total inputs there
are n minus l of these right but because
the weight is minus1 that becomes l
minus n and so under this condition this
sum is going to be l minus n but the
threshold is l - n + 1 so it won't fire
but if any of these become zero
then this my weight minus one will not
apply and So then the total sum will
actually match or exceed L minus N +1
and it will fire. So also if any of
these becomes one that's going to add to
the total sum and it's going to match or
exceed L - N +1 and it will fire. So
this unit fires if any of these guys are
one or if any of these guys are zero.
It's a universal orgate. Did this make
sense to you guys?
This makes sense to you guys yes or no
right it's very straightforward so now
you can also do other things uh
perceptrons
are
uh can also act as majority gates this
perceptron will fire if at least k of
the inputs are one and you can see why
if at least k of the inputs are one it's
going to match the threshold otherwise
it will not a single unit has a majority
gate. Whereas if you would try to
construct this using standard boolean
gates, you need an a large network with
an exponential number of gates to
compute the majority. And so you can see
why the perceptron is a very versatile
unit and can model all kinds of crazy
boolean functions by itself, which is
why some early researchers researchers
got fooled into thinking it could do any
boolean function at all. But then the
perceptron cannot model the simple exor.
There is no combination of weights or
and thresholds that will compute the XR.
We saw this in the last class. So to
compute an XR,
you have to network multiple of these
perceptrons and you need a multi-layer
perceptron. This for example is a
network that computes the XR. It's a
network of three perceptrons with one
hidden layer uh and one and one output
neuron.
Now the structure is rather obvious. The
first perceptron on top computes X or Y.
The bottom one in the second layer
computes not X or not Y. And the final
perceptron adds these two outputs. And
so you get an X X or Y. And in fact,
this is not the only way to build an NLP
to compose an XR. Here's a more compact
way that I got from Gerald Freedelland
at Berkeley. This unit, this uses only
two perceptrons. But now the weights are
all not all one. and let you figure out
how this works.
So the upshot of all of this is that we
can compute all basic boolean gates
using perceptrons. And so we can in fact
construct an MLP for any boolean
function like this weird one here uh
which computes a function of four
inputs. So MLPS are in fact universal
boolean functions. What I mean by this
is that if you give me any boolean
function at all, I can construct an MLP
to compute it.
So MLPS are universal boolean functions.
That statement make sense to you that
MLPS are universal boolean functions?
Yes. No. Okay. Uh all right. Great.
So MLPS are universal boolean functions.
They can be constructed to compute any
boolean function over any number of
inputs and any number of outputs.
But how complex will the network get? In
the example here on the left, we saw
that in order to construct a network for
this crazy boolean function, we had a
network with three layers and seven
neurons.
So the MLP that computes this network
has two hidden layers. If I had a more
complex function of a larger number of
inputs, how many layers would the MLP
need to have to compute it? How does the
depth of the network relate to the
complexity of the boolean function it
computes? Does anybody want to guess
how many layers 2 to n how many layers
must a network have to compute a really
complex boolean function?
so four okay I'm [clears throat] getting
a few different answers but then
consider this the claim is that I can do
it with one hidden layer and to see why
see the any boolean function is
basically just a truth table it takes a
number of inputs and computes an output
so I can write down a table where I
explicitly specify all the input
combinations and the corresponding
output. In fact, I don't need to write
the table for every possible
combination. I only need to write the
table for all the combinations that
produce an output of one. For the rest
of them, it uh the output is implicitly
zero. Once you write it in this manner,
you can write out the boolean function
in as a DNF or a disjunctive normal form
formula. And the DNF form formula has
clauses. One clause for every row, every
combination of inputs that produces a
one. So this first clause that produces
a one says that the output is one if x1
is 0, x2 is 0, x3 is 1, x4 is 1, and x5
is 0. In boolean terms, not x1, not x2,
x3, x4, not x5. The second row says not
x1, x2, not x3, x4, x5 and so on. So I
have one such clause for each one of
these rows. They are all odd as shown by
this plus. And this formula computes
this this truth table exactly. But now I
can build an MLP to construct this
formula using perceptrons that model
universal and and orgates. I can have
one perceptron for this first clause,
one for the second clause, one for the
third, one for the fourth, one for the
fifth, one for the sixth, and then
finally a perceptron that orders them
all. And this multi-layer perceptron
with just one hidden layer is able to
compute this truth table. And so the key
is that it does not matter
how big or how complex the truth table
is. You can model any boolean function
in this manner because any boolean
function can be explicit as a truth
table. And so any boolean function can
be composed using a multi-layer peretron
which has only one hidden layer. That
make sense to everybody?
Does that make sense to everybody? Okay.
Right. So easy enough.
But then if I do this with just one
hidden layer, what is the largest number
of perceptrons required in the single
hidden layer for an N input variable
function?
In other words, how large do these DNF
formula get? Can anybody guess?
So how large must this hidden layer be
in the worst case?
N plus2 N plus1. So some of you have got
the correct answer and let's see why
right to answer this let's take a look
at the truth table in a different way in
the form of a car map. How many of you
are familiar with car maps?
How many of you are familiar with car
maps?
Anybody?
So
okay
some folks are some folks are not. Now,
a car map is a topological way of
representing bit patterns such that bit
patterns that differ by only one bit are
[clears throat] always arranged next to
one another. For example, this is a
cardinal map over four variables wx, y
and z. The four rows represent all four
combinations of wx 0 0 1 1 and 1 0. And
observe that the way I've arranged it
adj adjacent rows differ in only one
bit. So these two differ in one bit.
These two differ in one bit. And note
that the bottommost row and the topmost
row also differ in only one bit. So this
top edge and this bottom edge are
virtually connected. Similarly the four
columns that represent the four
combinations of YZ. They're also
arranged so that adjacent columns only
differ in one bit and the rightmost edge
uh is connected to the leftmost edge. So
this although I've shown it as a square,
it's actually a Taurus and each cell
over here represents one combination of
inputs. So is this topological
representation making sense?
This topological representation. Okay.
And so
now instead of having a truth table, I'm
just going to highlight the cells for
which the output is one. And so here
if I I have seven
input combinations for which the output
is one. So a naive DNF formula would
have seven clauses. But then now we can
begin grouping neighbor neighboring
boxes to reduce the size of the DNF
formula. So here, these four guys,
they're all neighboring. I can group
them up because what these four guys are
telling me is that it does not matter
what w and x are. So long as y and y and
z take the value 0 0,
the output is one. And so these four
boxes together can be represented by a
single clause not y not z. Similarly,
these two guys, they tell me that so
long as W and X are zero and one and so
long as Y is zero, it doesn't matter
what Z is because the difference between
these two columns is just Z, right? And
so these two guys can be grouped into a
single clause. Not Y, X, I mean not W,
X, not Y. And so also these two guys, in
fact I can group all four of four
corners and they they're going to give
me a single clause not X Y not Z. And so
this DNA reduced DNF formula doesn't
have seven elements. It has only three.
And therefore a single hidden layer MLP
that computes the this boolean function
for this truth table only has three
neurons and a hidden layer. And so long
as the entries in the truth table can be
grouped in this manner, we can keep
shrinking the DNF formula. And so the
DNF formula that expresses it can be
made smaller and smaller and the
resulting network will be small. But we
are interested in knowing the worst
case. How large the one layer boolean
MLP can get uh in the absolute worst
case. Again, we're speaking of a one
hidden layer MLP, right? So what
arrangement of highlighted cells simply
cannot be grouped together and reduced?
Anybody want to tell me? Checkerboard,
right? So if I have a checkerboard of
this kind,
then there's no way for me to be
grouping elements. So how many clauses
would the DNF formula for this
checkerboard require?
How many?
Anybody?
eight right
now.
Sorry.
Here's a three-dimensional version of
the same thing. This is a 3D version of
a car map on six input variables UV, wx,
and yz. How many neurons would be
required in the hidden layer for a one
hidden layer MLP that computes this
boolean function? Anyone?
32. Right. So we can this can be
generalized. If you have a boolean
function over n variables and you
construct a one hidden layer MLP to
compose the corresponding DNF formula,
you will end up needing 2 ra to n minus1
neurons in the hidden layer. The size of
the network in terms of the required
neurons is exponential in the number of
inputs. [clears throat]
This make sense to everybody?
This make sense? Does this make sense to
everybody? Yes or no? Okay, I'm assuming
there are lots of thumbs ups. And so
that gives us our next
poll.
10 seconds, guys.
All right, let me stop this.
Okay, somebody want to tell me the
answer.
What is the answer? 512. Right? So
indeed that is the correct answer.
Beautiful. So you guys got it.
Now this can be generalized. So to
reiterate, if you only allow one hidden
layer, this pattern over n inputs
requires an exponential number of
neurons to raise to n minus one neurons
in the hidden layer. But uh
what would be the size of the network if
we allowed multiple hidden pairs? Now
does anybody recognize this function?
What is this function with a
checkerboard? Can anybody tell me what's
this function with a checkerboard?
anyone.
What is this function? It's an XR,
right? Thank you. So,
this function represented by these
checkerboards is actually just an XR. An
XR is just a function where if you
change just one bit, the output goes
from 0 to one. If the number of bits,
the total number of ones is even, the
output is zero. If it's odd, the output
is one. And so this is wx or xx or y x
or z. This is ux or vx or wx or x x or y
x or z. And we know that an xr can be
constructed using only three neurons
in two layers or even just two
perceptrons. Right? And so for this
function we can construct the mlp as a
series of exors like here. The first
three neurons compute the XR of W and X.
Then the next three neurons XR that
result with Y. The next three neurons XR
that result with Z. And so totally we're
going to need only
nine neurons. Now again even if we
directly implemented this using just the
straight up DNF formula, it still need
nine neurons. So it doesn't look like we
won out here. But then if you go to the
larger networks like this one, this is a
function of six variables which has five
XRS. The XR based network which looks
over here only needs 15 perceptrons
whereas the one hidden layer network
required 33.
Generalizing this to n inputs,
the xr of n input variables will just
require 3 * n minus one or even 2 * n
minus one neurons when built in this
manner. And so we have this right
when you have an exord of n inputs a
naive single hidden layer MLP will
require to require 2 to n -1 + 1 neurons
which is exponential in n.
Whereas a deep network where you're
allowed to have as many hidden layers as
you want will require only 3 * n minus
one perceptrons. This is linear in n. So
when you make the network shallow the
number of neurons is exponential. When
you allow it to be deep it ends up being
linear in the input. And moreover these
three n 3 * n minus one neurons can be
arranged in only two times log 2 n
layers. So did all of this make sense so
far guys?
Did all of this make sense?
Okay. So let's see how we can arrange
this only in two times login layers.
Here's how you do this. The XR is
associated which means you can group the
operations in any way and the output
will still be the same. So we can first
compute the XR of the first two inputs
separately comput of the next two inputs
then compute the XR of the next two
inputs and so on. You can compute XR
pair-wise. And so the outcome of that
operation is going to be a series of
values each of which is the exor of two
terms. Then those things can be paired
up and exort. And then you can you're
going to get a series of values which
are at x of two terms at this level
which is four terms at this level. And
those can be exort pair-wise and so on.
And so here is the kind of structure you
would get
that each now again each XR of course
requires two two layers right. So over
here each pair of layers highlighted in
a blue box is producing a set of
variables that can be further exor
downstream.
And each blue box reduces the number of
variables by a factor of two.
And so what this means is that the total
number of these blue boxes is going to
be log 2 of n. Within each blue box you
have two layers. So the total number of
layers is 2 * log 2 of n. And so if you
allow the network to be deep, the number
of neurons is going to be linear in the
number of inputs and the number of
layers is required is going to be
logarithmic and the number of inputs.
That make sense to everybody?
Okay, beautiful, right?
But then what happens if you terminate
the network early after just a few
layers? So let me say that I don't want
the network to have login layers. I want
to want it to have at most four layers.
Then in the best case, the first two
layers can be used to reduce the number
of variables by two. But the rest of
them still have to be exorked. And
because after that you you're only
allowed one more hidden layer. This
layer is going to be the size of this
layer is going to be exponential in the
number of variables over here. And so
effectively it's going to be exponential
in the number of inputs. So if you use
fewer than the minimum uh required if
you if you use fewer than uh two times
login layers or more generally if you
use a fixed number of layers then to
model the net function exactly you're
going to require an exponential number
of neurons and if you try to take a
shortcut and try to go below that number
of neurons then the results can be
horrible. In fact, for the XR, if you
just go one neuron below the minimum,
then the error of the XR is going to be
50%. Because that's the function, that's
the kind of fun function the XR is. That
makes sense to you guys.
Why? If you have a fixed number of
layers or if you have fewer than the
minimum required number of layers, then
the network has to be exponentially wide
or it's going to be very long.
That make sense to everybody?
Yes or no?
I see two S's. Any questions?
>> We have a question in the chat.
>> Okay. What is the question?
>> So, will two end layers usually be the
optimal starting point when deciding
ideally the problem is that we don't
know the function here. I'm assuming
it's an exor a more general boolean
function. A more general function can be
anything. And so the optimal number of
layers can't really be known for the
function. But in the worst case, it has
to be log to n. Okay,
if you have log to n layers, then you
can expect to be able to model functions
with a linear number of neurons.
Now the thing is uh this means that the
depth of the network depends on the
number of inputs. More generally, when
you build neural networks, you decide on
the depth of the network regardless of
the size of the input and so you just
end up falling into this condition and
as a result your networks end up needing
to be very large simply because you're
not matching the optimal depth.
And so to recap, deep boolean MLPS that
scale linearly in size of the number of
inputs can become exponentially large if
we cast using only one hidden layer or
even a fixed number of hidden layers
where the number of hidden layers is
independent of the number of variables
in the input. And so in summary
uh an MLP is a universal boolean
function but can represent a given
function only if it's sufficiently wide
if it's sufficiently deep if depth can
be traded off for but depth can be
traded off for sometimes exponential
growth of the width of the network.
optimal width and depth depend on the
number of variables and the complexity
of the boolean function where the
complexity can be defined in terms of
the minimal number of terms and the DNF
formula for the function
and so so our story so far is that
multi-layer perceptrons are universal
boolean machines even a network with a
single hidden layer is a universal
boolean machine but a single layer
network may require an exponentially
large number of perceptrons deeper
networks may require far fewer neurons
in shallower networks to express the
same function. They could be
exponentially smaller.
So we've seen MLPS as universal
functions. But then let's move on to
MLPS as universal classifiers and the
need for depth.
We've already seen that an MLP can
operate as a boolean function over real
inputs. Basically as a classifier, a
boolean function will effectively
partition the input space into regions
where the output is one and regions
where the output is zero. And therefore
it's able to
act operate as a classifier where it
separates out the data within the region
where the output is one from the data
where uh in the region where the output
is zero.
And we've also seen that the network and
model compute some very complex uh
decision boundaries.
But before discussing multi-layer
perceptrons, let's first consider a
single perceptron. To recap, a
perceptron uses this criterion for its
output. If the weighted sum exceeds the
exceeds the threshold, the output is
one. If it's less than the threshold,
the output is zero. The boundary between
the between the two is where the
weighted sum is exactly equal to a
threshold. That's going to be a hyper
plane and on one side of the hyper plane
the output is one the other side it's
zero.
The so the perceptron overall models
this models this heavy side function
where there's a hyper plane on one side
the output is zero and the other side
the output is one.
But then uh once you understand this you
can see how it can compute boolean
gates. If the input is boolean if you
have two boolean inputs the input
combinations can be 0 0 1 0 0 1 or 1 1.
And so the input combinations can be
only one of these four dots. If the
weights of the perceptron are set such
that this boundary between the one and
the zero falls in this region, then this
captures a specific boolean gate. What
was the boolean gate this captured?
This is an R. And this guy, if the
weights were like this, this what did
this capture? The output is one over
here.
It's a not on a Y. It's ignoring X,
right? And now you can see why it cannot
capture an XR. An XR actually needs two
boundaries because the output is one for
these two combinations and zero for
these two combinations. Whereas a
perceptron can only model one boundary.
Which is why a single XR cannot single
perceptron cannot model an XR.
And that leads us to our third pole.
Where is that? I put third pole.
15 seconds, guys.
All right, let me end this poll and let
me ask you
what is the answer.
It's true, right? So
an XR needs two hidden neurons and one
output neuron because we need one hidden
neuron for the two boundaries and an
output neuron to add them. Beautiful.
But once we have that the basic
perceptron we saw how we could compose
decision boundaries like this pentagon.
You want the net to output of one inside
the pentagon and zero outside. So we
compose one perceptron for each of the
five boundaries like so. And then
finally you so each perceptron is going
to be outputting a one in the
highlighted region and a zero in the
non- highlighted region. And so finally
you find that only the pentagon is the
only region where all five perceptrons
output a one. So if you sum the outputs
of the five perceptrons it's going to be
a five inside the pentagon and less than
five outside.
And now this final perceptron can simply
compare this sum to a threshold of five
and it's going to capture the uh
pentagon decision boundary. But once you
know how to compose a pentagon decision
boundary, you can compose more complex
boundaries. for example, this double
pentagon. Uh, and we'd have one subnet
that outputs a one inside the first
pentagon, a second subnet which outputs
a one inside the second pentagon, and
then a final neuron which cores these
two. And this is going to give you the
double pentagon.
Once you know how this how to do this,
using the same mechanism, you can
compose even more complex decision
boundaries like the ones on this slide.
For example, for this decision boundary,
we can partition it into many sub
regions, compose a subnet for each sub
region, and then or the lot and that's
going to give you this crazy decision
boundary. You can use the same mechanism
to compose any arbitrarily complex
decision boundary.
But the circuit we compose for this
actually has two hidden layers. Can we
do this with only one hidden layer? And
if so, how? To make this more concrete,
to give you a simpler example, can
anybody suggest how I can compose a
network of this kind with only one
hidden layer which captures this
decision boundary?
Any suggestions?
How would we do this
with just one decision boundary? anyone
had a layer each side is of course a
perceptron but
exor xors need to you know leong says is
it possible that's actually a good
question how would you do this any
suggestion not possible okay some of you
are probably thinking that you know I
can just have one perceptron for each of
these boundaries but if I do that go
back and look here right you had the the
sum was four in this region and here and
here and here. So because the sum is
four in these regions, if I just have
one perceptron for each of these
uh pentagons,
then the sum is going to be four over
here from these five. It's also going to
be four over here from these five. And
so in this region, although it's neither
in this pentagon or in this pentagon,
the sum is going to end up being eight,
which is probably going to be higher
than the sums inside the double
pentagons. And so you're going to end up
you'll get the double pentagon, but
you'll get a lot of speurious regions
because
specifically of these regions over here
where the sum is almost five but not
quite five.
And we need a solution that makes sure
that the sum is not close to the to five
inside. That make sense to you guys?
Did did that make sense to you guys?
Right. What we just the logic I gave?
Okay. So, how do we get around that?
To get around see how we how we get
around that. Let's start with a simple
diamond shaped decision boundary. We can
do this with four hidden neurons, one
for each of these boundaries and then
the final final and. So if I just plot
the sum of the output of these four
neurons, the sum of the output of these
four neurons is going to look like this.
It's four over here. It's three in these
strips which is infinitely which goes
off to infinite which go off to infinity
and it's two in these little blue
regions. So if I apply a threshold of
four, I'm going to get a decision
boundary that's a a diamond but then
keep track of these regions where the
sum is three that's for a diamond if I
go I go to a pentagon then again now I
need five neurons in the hidden layer
but the sum of the output of these five
neurons looks like this
that it's five in the pentagon but the
region where the sum is four has
actually become the star which is kind
of over here for when I when I had only
four sides the region where the sum was
three went off to infinity here. The
region where the sum is four n minus one
is actually finite and this star- shaped
region. If I make it a hexagon, then I
have six hidden neurons, one for each
side. But if I look at the sum of these
outputs, it's going to be six inside.
But the region where the sum is five is
an even smaller star. If I make it a
heptagon, I'm only plotting the sum. You
can see that the region where the sum is
six and not seven has become even
smaller. Where the sum is five is also
finite. With 16 sides, this is the
figure we get. With 64 sides, this is
the figure we get. This is what you get
with a th00and sides.
And so we see that as we increase the
number of sides to the polygon for an
n-sided polygon the area within which
the sum of the outputs of the hidden
layer is just is not quite equal to n
but high enough to cause problems keeps
shrinking.
That make sense to everybody?
This makes sense to everybody? Yes.
Right. And so do we have thumbs up Brad?
Okay,
>> we do.
>> So what was the problem here Jesse? Your
question can you clarify your doubt? Ask
me out.
>> Yeah, this last part that you said when
we have like more uh more polygons like
the more size of the polygons I didn't
get it well. So here I'm just plotting
the sum of the output of these neurons.
And you can see why the sum is four
inside, three over here, and two over
here. Right? Do you get that?
>> Yes.
>> I did that for five pentagons. It's five
here. The sum in the various regions.
Did this figure make sense?
>> Yes.
>> This is I'm plotting the same thing as I
keep increasing the number of sides.
That makes sense.
Yeah.
>> Okay. And in the limit,
you know, we're going to find that the
uh
that as we increase the number of sides
for an ns-sided polygon, the area within
which the sum of the outputs lies
between n /2 and n keeps decreasing. in
the limit is you're actually going to
get this function over here which looks
uh this which has this crazy formula
which one of my TAS once worked out
worked out but uh if you simplify it
if you have an infinite number of sides
that's a circle and then if I have
neurons for every side the sum of the
outputs is going as n becomes very large
you're going to eventually end up with a
network where the sum is exactly n
inside the circle circle and n /2
everywhere everywhere outside almost
everywhere outside then you can place
the circle anywhere you want and
furthermore if I subtract and the n /2
from the sum I'm going to end up with a
network where the sum is exactly n /2
inside the circle and exactly zero
everywhere else.
So now if I want to compose
uh if I if I add two such networks
where this first network the sum of
these neurons is this cylinder the
second network is the this set of
neurons whose sum is given by this
cylinder again they're they're just
different copies of these this cylinder
in different locations because you can
place them anywhere. Then the sum of the
outputs of both of these networks is
going to be two cylinders like this with
the height being n /2 inside the
cylinders and zero outside. Did that
make sense to everybody?
Right. And so
any questions on this graph? Do you see
any questions in chat? Okay.
And so this is beautiful. I can now use
a threshold of n /2 and I'm going to get
a decision boundary which is two
disconnected circles.
And if I can place two disconnected
circles, then I can make any odd
decision boundary. If I want to compose
this double pentagon using only one
hidden layer, we will do so by
approximating it as a union of many
little circles. Each one using its own
little subnet of hidden neurons. And you
can make the approximation arbitrarily
precise by filling it with more and more
smaller circles. And so you can
approximate the double pentagon to
arbitrary precision using only one
hidden layer. Although this will require
an impossibly large number of neurons in
the hidden layer.
And thus we have this MLPS can capture
any classification boundary. Even a one
hidden layer MLP can
uh approximate any classification
boundary to arbitrary precision. So your
MLPS are universal classifiers. Again,
what this means is that you give me a
classification boundary and I can
compose an MLP that computes it.
And in fact, I can compose an MLP with
just one hidden layer that computes it.
But we the thing is if I simply make the
network deeper like in this case the
number of neurons falls dramatically. If
I just wanted only one hidden layer I
needed almost infinite neurons and I
only got an approximation to the
decision boundary. Whereas as soon as I
let the network go deep, the uh number
of neurons required became finite and my
approximation and and and the and the
accuracy with which I modeled the
boundary became better and better.
So this makes sense to everybody. Does
this make sense?
Which is why you need depth really
matters even for classification.
We know deeper network networks are bit
better. But why? To get a better idea,
let's look at a different kind of
decision boundary which is a bit of a
worst case decision boundary. We will
analyze threshold activation networks.
But this should generalize to other
networks as well. Consider this decision
boundary. This network must output a one
when the input is in the yellow regions
and zero for the gray regions. Now, if I
build a naive one hidden layer neural
network, as we just saw, I'm going to
have to fill all of these yellow regions
with little circles. And so, you're
going to need a network with almost
infinite neurons in the hidden layer.
But if I do this with two hidden layers,
I need only 56 neurons. That's because
this decision boundary over here is
composed of 16 lines. And so uh uh here
the 16 lines are shown here in the top
left each of these red lines. And so we
need 16 perceptrons to capture each one
of these 16 lines. Then there are 40 of
these yellow regions in all. So we will
need 40 perceptrons in the second hidden
layer. One to capture each one of these
yellow regions. And then we need a final
perceptron to order the outputs of these
neurons. And so this network if I allow
two hidden layers requires 57 total
neurons including the output neuron.
But then can I make it smaller?
This is just an XR pattern, right?
If we number the outputs of these first
16 neurons as Y1 through Y16,
then this entire pattern is simply going
to be an XR of Y1 through Y16.
So if I compose this using an XR
network, the XOR part of it because
there are 16 of these guys are only is
is only going to require 15 * 3 neurons,
45 neurons. In fact, if I if I compose
each XR using the two neuron network
from Gerald Freedelland, it's only going
to require 15 * 2 30 neurons. And so,
the overall network would require only
46 neurons as opposed to the uh 57
neurons. Now in this example maybe it
doesn't seem like a big win but if I
came went to something more complex like
this decision boundary this is composed
of 64 lines and we want the network to
output of one for the inputs in the
yellow regions. You can capture the 64
lines with one hidden layer of 64
perceptrons.
There are 544
of these yellow regions in the second
layer. So in so including the output
neuron you're going to have 544 neurons
over here 641 neurons here this guy over
here the total number of neurons is
going to be 609 neurons but once again
this is just an XR over the 64 lines. So
a 7 layer XR network that uses three
neurons per XR can do this with only 253
neurons. If I use two neurons per ex,
the network will require only
190 neurons as opposed to 609.
And so the difference in size between
the deeper optimal network and the
shallower network increases with
increasing pattern complexity and input
dimension. Now note that I'm not
comparing a network with one hidden
layer with a deep network. This network
in fact has two hidden layers. But even
with two hidden layers, this ends up
requiring many more neurons than
something that is much deeper.
And so the depth summary is that the
number of neurons required in a shallow
network can be potentially exponential
in the dimensionality of the input in
the worst case or exponential in the
statistic in the uh in number of
statistically independent features. But
even if you allow networks of different
depths, the deeper network will often
require far fewer network neurons than
the less deep network.
And so the story so far, multi-layer
perceptrons are universal boolean
machines. Even a network with a single
hidden layer is a universal boolean
machine.
And we've seen that multi-layer
perceptrons are also universal
classification functions. Even a network
with a single hidden layer is a
universal classifier.
But a single hidden layer network may
require an exponentially large number of
perceptrons more than a deep one. And
deeper networks in general may require
far fewer neurons than shallower
networks to express the same function.
Could be exponentially smaller. But even
if it's not exponentially smaller, as we
saw in the case of the little yellow
checkerboard, a network that was deep
require can end up requiring
much much much fewer neurons than a
network that is less deep.
Did that that make sense to all of you
guys?
That make sense
what we've covered so far? Yes. No.
Any other yeses? Are there thumbs up,
Brad? I can't see them for some reason.
>> Yeah, there are tons.
>> I see some I got 29 thumbs ups. I'm
going to wait for 60 of them, right? So,
uh, the next time around, I'd like to
make sure that at least 20% of my class
got it.
Okay, I think I have 60.
All right.
And so, let's go on. Finally as uh MLPS
as universal approximators. We've seen
their universal boolean functions,
universal classifiers. Uh how about as
approximators? We saw that an MLP with
two perceptrons can compute a this step
function, a pulse over a scalar input.
The two perceptrons have different
thresholds T1 and T2. Their outputs are
summed with weight one and minus one.
And so when the input is less than T1,
neither of them will fire and the output
is zero. When the input is between T1
and T2, this neuron will fire but this
will not. So the sum is going to be one.
When the input is greater than T2, both
of them fire, they cancel each other out
and the output becomes zero again. But
then subsequently we can compose any
scalar function of a scalar variable
with a one hidden layer MLP by
approximating the function of many
function as a sum of many such pulses
all scale to the right height. So a one
hidden layer MLP can model arbitrary
arbitrary scalar functions of a scalar
variable.
For functions of higher dimensions it
gets trick trickier. We begin by
recalling that a one hidden layer NLP
can compose a cylinder that has height n
/2 inside and zero outside. And so to
compose an arbitrary function in iron
dimensions, you can approximate it by
summing appropriately scaled and shifted
cylinders and you can approximate it to
arbitrary precision by making the
cylinders thinner. So one hidden layer
MLP is a universal
function approximator.
And so here's our fourth pole.
I also have a fifth pole, but people
don't know how to
only give you 30 seconds for this, guys.
So 10 seconds more.
Okay, let me end this.
What is the answer, guys?
It's false. It's false because it can
only be approximated, right?
Finally, let's briefly discuss the issue
of sufficiency of width and depth and
its relation to the activation function.
We've seen so far that a single hidden
layer MLP is a universal function
approximator. It can approximate any
function to arbitrary precision. More
generally, deeper networks we saw will
require far fewer neurons for the same
approximation error for boolean
functions, classifiers, and re real
value functions. But there are
limitations. And where do these come
from?
Now we saw that this neural network can
this neural network with 16 hidden
neurons and 40 neurons in the second
layer can can capture this decision
boundary.
So our claim is that a neural network
can represent any function provided it
has sufficient capacity if it's
sufficiently broad and sufficiently deep
to represent the function here. If it
has 16 neurons here and 40 here, it's
good enough to model this function. But
what if it had only eight neurons in the
first layer? I'm going to assume we have
threshold activation functions.
Then
would it be still be able to capture
this function? What do you guys think?
If I only have eight neurons in the
hidden layer in in the first layer,
would it still be able to model this
function?
So, Praad says no. And the answer is no.
Why? Say the eight neurons capture these
eight lines as shown in that are shown
in red. Now, the output if I'm using
threshold activations, then the output
of the first layer is only going to tell
me, you know, because the output is
either one or zero for each of these
neurons, right? The output is only going
to tell me in which of these strips the
input is. but provides no additional
information about where you are in the
strip. So it doesn't matter how many
neurons I put in subsequent uh layers. I
do not have the information to capture
reconstruct the checkerboard. Even if
the eight neurons capture these eight
lines, you'll only have the level of
information shown here. You can
determine which of these 25 regions the
input is in. But you cannot improve
beyond that because you you don't know
where you are within the region.
Regardless of how many layers or neurons
you add afterwards, you cannot recover
the checkerboard.
So also if you even have even if you
have a full complement of 16 perceptrons
in the first hidden layer, if you have
only two layers and fewer than 40
neurons in the second layer, you cannot
compose this per function perfectly. In
other words, if you make your network
deep rather than wide, you have to
ensure that each layer is still
sufficiently wide [clears throat] to
transmit the information required. If if
not, it does not matter how deep you
make your network, you cannot model your
function.
So, but there's a caveat and let's come
to the caveat. We saw that a network
with fewer than 16 neurons in the first
layer could never compose a decision
decision pattern. Why? This is because
in all of our explanations, we used
threshold activations which gates
information in the input and prevents it
from reaching later layers. So if you
had only four neurons in the first
layer, each neuron will tell you whether
the input is on one side of a boundary
or not, but it won't tell you how far
you are from the boundary. As a result,
if you had only four neurons in the
first layer,
the output of the first layer will
partition the input into a small set of
regions like this, but provides no
subsequent information and subsequent
layers cannot have cannot make up for
this loss of information.
This happens because we use threshold
activations which lost information about
how far you are from the boundary. If on
the other hand you used a continuous
activation like a sigmoid it will
produce a graded output like this one
and so the output of the sigmoid will
tell you how far you are from the
boundary and that can provide the
information to subsequent layers which
may then be able to use that to compose
the rest of the function.
But a sigmoid is not great in the sense
right you can see that once you get past
these dotted lines then the variation of
the sigmoid as a function of the
distance from the boundary basically
vanishes to almost zero. So having more
informative activation functions like
this guy like a reloop which continues
to inform about how far you are from the
boundary forever at least on one side of
the boundary or a soft or a leaky rail
which continues to inform how far you
are from the boundary on both sides of
the boundary. These are better
activations which where the first layer
outputs will continue to give you
information. They'll give subsequent
layers information that they can then
use to compose the decision boundary
properly.
And so narrow layers can still pass
sufficient information to subsequent
layers provided the activation function
is sufficiently graded.
But in order to completely capture the
function, we will need greater depth in
the network to permit later layers to
capture the details of the function.
So did all of this make sense to you
guys?
The the why we need activations that are
not threshold activations.
Theations
is that they're only going to give you
this kind of information. smoother
activations will tell you how far you
are from the boundary. So these neurons
will continue to give information about
how far you are from the boundary and
then the subsequent layers can use it to
compose the con compose the uh the uh
compose the rest of the pattern. Right?
So the thing is that you're still kind
of hoping
that you get things right. For example,
if I have four neurons and the four
neurons are just like this, then you do
not have information in this direction.
So you still cannot compose uh the
entire boundary. If you want if you have
only four neurons, you want your four
neurons to capture boundaries of this
kind, which is when you'll be able to
reconstruct the entire checkerboard.
Otherwise, you don't have information in
this direction and you won't be able to
construct the checkerboard. So you need
graded outputs. But even then there is
more to it than that for you to be able
to capture your model capture your uh
boundaries your function properly. And
so the lesson so far MLPS are universal
function approximities. They can model
any boolean function classification
functional regression. Deeper MLPS can
achieve the same precision with far
fewer neurons but must still have
sufficient capacity.
The activations must pass information
through and each layer must be
sufficiently wide to convey all the
relevant information to subsequent
layers.
I have a poll which I will skip. We keep
talking about the capacity of a network.
What exactly is the capacity of the
network? There have been various
definitions based on information of
storage capacity, VC dimension and so
on. From our perspective, it's the
largest number of disconnected regions
of the input that the network can
represent.
uh and the point is a network with
insufficient capacity cannot model a
function that requires greater minimal
number of uh a larger network than the a
network with a larger capacity than what
your network currently has. So uh even
more definitions
maybe later in the course if I have the
uh an extra lecture I'll ask Gerald
Freland to give a lecture on this topic
and so here are the lessons today MLPS
are boolean functions universal boolean
functions universal classifiers
universal function approximators even a
single layer MLP can approximate
anything to arbitrary precision but
could be exponentially or even
infinitely wide in its input size.
Deeper MLPS can achieve the same
precision with far fewer neurons. In
other words, they're more expressive.
Also, more graded activation functions
result in more expressive networks. Next
up, we know that MLPS can emulate any
function, but how do we make them
emulate a specific desired function? For
example, if you want a function takes an
input and labels outputs the labels of
all the objects in it or takes in speech
and produces transcriptions. How do you
compose a network that computes this
function? That is training and NLP. And
we'll pick that up from the next class.
So I'll stop right here and I'll take
any questions.